Register of the Alexander Vardy Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Alexander Vardy papers
1940-2002
91014
Hoover Institution Archives
131 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 envelope (55.6 linear feet)
Writings, transcripts and sound recordings of Radio Liberty broadcasts, Radio Liberty memoranda and other internal documents, and reports, studies, newsletters, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Radio Liberty broadcasts to the Soviet Union, and to Soviet politics, culture and society.
Vardy, Alexander, 1916-1991
Access
Collection stored off site; a minimum of two days notice is required for use. Boxes may be requested through Stanford's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in increments from 1991 to 2002.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1916 September 10 Born, Smolensk, Russia (Aleksandr Markovich Lifits)
1933 Graduated from high school
1933-1936 Attended the Moscow Technical Institute for Mechanics and Moscow University Law School
1936 Arrested for "anti Soviet propaganda" and sentenced to three years of forced labor for defending Einstein's relativity theory
1939 Released from the camp
1941 Graduated from an engineering college
1941-1945 Fought in the Soviet Army
1945-1950 Engineer and Senior Engineer in the State Highway Directorate (Gosudarstvennoe Upravlenie Shosseinykh Dorog SSSR - Gushosdor)
1950 Arrested as a "political recidivist"
1950-1955 Sentenced to ten years of forced labor camps, but released after five years
1955-1957 Senior official in a factory, Stanislav
1956 Rehabilitated
1957 Left the Soviet Union for Poland, then emigrated to Israel
1962 Joined Radio Liberty, Munich, Germany
1963-1981 Broadcaster, Radio Liberty
1964 Author, Prorub'
1971 Author, Podkonvoinyi mir
1983 Settled in California
1991 May 2 Died, Hayward, California
Scope and Content Note
This collection of papers of Alexander Vardy (Aleksandr Markovich Lifits) primarily covers Vardy's work for Radio Liberty in Munich from 1963 to his retirement in 1980. It includes broadcast transcripts; correspondence; labor camp anecdotes, poetry, and songs; printed matter; and writings. Phonotapes of broadcasts, interviews, and songs are also included.
Born in Smolensk, Vardy had by 1936 finished three semesters at the Technical Institute for Mechanics in Moscow and studied law at the Moscow Law School. In 1936 he was arrested and kept in the prisons of Lubianka and Butyrka. The same year he was sentenced to three years in forced labor camps. Released in 1939, he returned home and graduated from engineering college in 1941.
In July 1941 Vardy was mobilized to join the Soviet Army and fought the Germans until the end of World War II. He was arrested again in 1950 as a "political recidivist" and sentenced to ten years in transpolar forced labor camps. After five years Vardy was released and rehabilitated.
In 1957 Alexander Vardy and his family left for Poland, and later the same year he emigrated to Israel. His 146 articles and book The Ice Hole were published in Israel and abroad.
In 1962 Vardy joined Radio Liberty in Munich, West Germany. From 1963 to his retirement in 1980 he wrote and produced more then 2000 radio programs about Soviet science, ideology, politics and economics.
The largest and perhaps most interesting series of papers is RADIO LIBERTY BROADCAST TRANSCRIPTS, which documents not only Vardy's broadcasts, but also a huge variety of other Radio Liberty broadcasts about events and people. Famous authors and Russian dissidents are the subject of, wrote, or otherwise participated in many of the programs for which transcripts are available.
Also of interest is the material relating to Vardy's publications, including articles and notes about Jews, German and Soviet media on anti-Semitism and Nazism; and two books, The Ice Hole and World Under Convoy, about Russian concentration camps.
The series WRITINGS BY OTHERS contains works of famous Russian poets and writers.
Radio Liberty (Prague, Czech Republic); Germany.; Radio broadcasting--Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Russians--Germany.; Russians--United States.; Soviet Union--Civilization.; Soviet Union--Politics and government.; Soviet Union--Social conditions.; Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations.
- Biographical File, 1963-1980 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Agreement and identity papers, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1961-1979 (Box 1-2)
  Letters sent and received from individuals and organizations, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1962-1985 (Box 2-7)
  Articles, books, notes, and speeches, arranged in three categories (General, About Germans, About Jews, the last two being categories established by Vardy), and therein chronologically by title
- Radio Liberty General File, 1958-1982 (Box 7-19)
  Announcements, appeals, articles, bulletins, correspondence, fliers, internal documents, lists, memoranda, minutes of meetings, news clips, newsletter, notes, open letters, organizational chart, outline, policy manual, publications, report, summaries, surveys, telephone directories, clippings and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Radio Liberty Broadcast Transcripts, 1963-1989 (Box 20-92)
  Broadcast transcripts including clippings, notes and research material, arranged alphabetically first by subject, then by name of broadcaster or participant
- Soviet Labor Camps File, 1955-1980 (Box 93-104)
  Anecdotes, poetry, slang dictionaries, and songs, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Writings by Others, 1958-1987 (Box 104-112)
  Appeals, articles, interviews, lectures, press conferences, and speeches, arranged alphabetically by name of author
- Printed Matter, 1958-1976 (Box 112-114)
  Articles and brochures relating to various activities of Radio Liberty
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 114 and photo file)
  39 prints depicting Alexander Vardy, his wife Nomi Vardy, and representatives of Radio Liberty
- Audiotapes, 1963-1980 (Box 115-126)
  167 phonotapes and phonotape cassettes, arranged as broadcasts, interviews, and songs
- Oversize Material, 1955-1989 (Box 127)
  Scrapbook of clippings, collected by Vardy, relating to him
- Incremental Materials, 1940-2002 (Box 128-132)
  Biographical file, correspondence, speeches and writings, Radio Liberty general file, Soviet labor camps file, and Nomi Vardy file, arranged in the same order used for the original material. Some of the incremental speeches and writings provide dates for undated writings in the main series. A "see also" reference in the container list for the original acquisition notes related material in the increment
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1963-1980 (Box 1)
  General note
  See also INCREMENTAL MATERIALS/Biographical file
  - General (Folder 1: 1)
  - Agreement between Radio Liberty Committee and A. Vardy relating to the assignment and transfer of certain broadcasting rights to the Committee by the author, 1964 June 23 (Folder 1: 1-2)
  - Financial documents (Folder 1: 3)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1961-1979
  See also INCREMENTAL MATERIALS/Correspondence
  - Unidentified, 1961-1973 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Am Obeg Publishing House, 1965 (Folder 1: 5)
  - American Committee for Liberation, 1962 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Amnesty International, 1975-1978 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Berger, I., 1963 1969 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Braun, Maximilian, 1966 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Bravemen, Robert, 1964 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Bush, K., 1972 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Central Association of Political Emigrants from the USSR, 1960 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Deon, Michel, 1961 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Fedorov, L., 1961-1962 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Finkelshtein, L., 1967 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Fisherung, D., 1968 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Geisenheyner, Ernst W., 1962 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Giedroyc, Jerzy, 1962 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Goldstein, Michael, 1972 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Gordon, Elizabeth, 1968 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Goul, Roman, 1961 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Greiner, Hermann, 1969 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Grizlov, Sergey, 1964 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Gul, Roman, 1960 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Harari, Manya, 1960 (Folder 1: 25)
  - Hayward, Max, 1963-1965 (Folder 1: 26)
  - Institut Littéraire, 196(?) (Folder 1: 27)
  - International Seminar on the Economy of Tuscany, 1962 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Kasi, S., 1962-1964 (Folder 1: 29)
  - Koks, Arthur M., 1961 (Folder 1: 30)
  - Krotkov, I., 1968 (Folder 1: 31)
  - Kvarnit, N., 1965 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Lavrov, Esper, 1967 (Folder 1: 33)
  - Lecker, Carol, 1970 (Folder 1: 34)
  - Leonhard, Wolfgang, 1962 (Folder 1: 35)
  - Louria, Ywroham, 1962-1964 (Folder 1: 36)
  - Margolin, I., 1960 (Folder 1: 37)
  - Oren-Nadel, I., 1963 (Folder 1: 38)
  - Panin, D., 1973 (Folder 1: 39)
  - Patch, I., 1964-1966 (Folder 1: 40)
    Includes camp songs
  - Radio Liberty, 1966 (Folder 1: 41)
  - Ralis, Max, 1967 (Folder 1: 42)
  - Reader's Digest, 1961 (Folder 1: 43)
  - RIAS, Berlin, 1967-1968 (Folder 1: 44)
  - Riva, Valerio, 1962 (Folder 1: 45)
  - Ronalds, Francis, 1966-1972 (Folder 1: 46)
  - Sher, IAkov, 1971 (Folder 1: 47)
  - Shifrin, A., 1976 (Folder 1: 48)
  - Shults, G., 1966 (Folder 1: 49)
  - Shurer, H., 1964 (Folder 1: 50)
  - Smith, Gerald, 1978-1979 (Folder 1: 51)
  - Suvarin, Boris K., 1961 (Folder 1: 52)
  - Svenson, George, 1963 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Svetlanin, A., 1962 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Svirskii, Grigorii, 1974 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Tarasova, N., 1961-1962 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Treguboff, J. A., 1972-1973 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Vodoff, Serge, 1965-1966 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 2: 7)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1962-1985
  See also RADIO LIBERTY BROADCAST TRANSCRIPTS/By or with the participation of/Vardy, Alexander; and INCREMENTAL MATERIALS/Speeches and writings
  - General
    - "Biologicheskie nauki dobivaiut marksizm-leninizm,", n.d. (Folder 2: 8)
      See also INCREMENTAL MATERIALS/Speeches and writings
    - "Demokratiia i psikhologiia,", n.d. (Folder 2: 9)
    - "Dialekticheskii materializm i sovremennoe nauchnoe miroponimanie,", n.d. (Folder 2: 10)
    - "Dialektika-eto dedushkiny skazki,", n.d. (Folder 2: 11)
    - "Evoliutstiia sovetskoi penitentsiarnoi praktiki," talks 1-5, n.d. (Folder 2: 12)
    - "Germany after the Holocaust,", n.d. (Folder 2: 13)
    - "Kakim obrazom mozhno osushchestvit' podlinnoe sblizheniie zapada i vostoka?", n.d. (Folder 2: 14)
    - "Karl Marks o Rossii i russkikh,", n.d. (Folder 2: 15)
    - "Kommunistische Philosophie: Analyse und Alternativen," (Folder 2: 16)
    - "Kto zhe vse-taki 'glupets' i kto 'providets'?", n.d. (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - "Na 14-om Mezhdunarodnom Filosofskom Kongresse,", n.d. (Folder 3: 2)
    - "Nauka razvenchivaet marksizm-leninizm,", n.d. (Folder 3: 3)
    - "Novyi etap revizionizma,", n.d. (Folder 3: 4)
    - "O filosofii sotsializma,", n.d. (Folder 3: 5)
    - "O knige Alberta Parry Raskol novogo klassa,", n.d. (Folder 3: 6)
    - "O knige S. Shvarttsa Evrei v Sovetskom Soiuze s nachala Vtoroi mirovoi voiny (1939-1965),", n.d. (Folder 3: 7)
    - "O knige S. Schwarz Sovetskii Soiuz i arabo-izrail'skaia voina 1967 goda,", n.d. (Folder 3: 8)
    - "O konflikte mezhdu 'Teoreticheskim frontom' Tsentral'nogo Komiteta KPSS i peredovymi biologami,", n.d. (Folder 3: 9)
    - "O marksistsko-leninskoi dialektike s pozitsii sovremennogo nauchnogo mirovozzreniia,", n.d. (Folder 3: 10)
    - "O metodologii sovetskoi filosofii, istorii s pozitsii sovremennogo nauchnogo mirovozzreniia,", n.d.
  - General
    - "O Mezhdunarodnom Kommunisticheskom Simpoziume 'Dialektika i sovremennoe estestvoznanie,", n.d. (Folder 3: 12)
    - "O 'Poedinke' parapsikhologii s filosofiei marksizma-leninizma,", n.d. (Folder 3: 13)
    - "O preobrazovanii Ministerstva Vnutrennikh Del v Ministerstvo Okhrany Obshchestvennogo Poriadka,", n.d. (Folder 3: 14)
    - "O radioperedachakh,", n.d. (Folder 3: 15)
    - "O razdvoenii edinogo,", n.d. (Folder 3: 16)
    - "O veroiatnostnom kharaktere obshchestvennykh zakonomernostei,", n.d. (Folder 3: 17)
    - "Obshchii rynok obostriaet krizis,", n.d. (Folder 3: 18)
    - "Ofitsial'noe priznanie nesostoiatel'nosti marksistsko-leninskoi dialektiki,", n.d. (Folder 3: 19)
    - "Organy iustitsii narushaiut ugolovnyi kodeks,", n.d. (Folder 3: 20)
    - "Razvitie svobodnogo mira po tret'emu puti,", n.d. (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - "Russkaia programma na piatnitsu 23-go fevralia 1962 g.,", n.d. (Folder 4: 2)
    - "Zagovor protiv psikhiki,", n.d. (Folder 4: 3)
    - Prorub', 1964
      - Authors' statement (Folder 4: 4)
      - Dictionary of terms used in Prorub' (Folder 4: 5)
      - List of the main characters (Folder 4: 6)
      - Printed copies
        - General (Folder 4: 7-8)
        - Drawings (Folder 4: 9)
      - Radio broadcast transcripts (Folder 4: 10)
      - Reviews (mostly in the Israeli media) (Box-folder 5: 1-3)
      - Translations
        - English (Folder 5: 4)
        - German (Folder 5: 5)
    - "Kommunisty i sionizm,", 1967 December (Folder 5: 6)
    - "Materialisticheskaia dialektika i sovremennoe estestvoznanie,", 1968 March (Folder 5: 7)
    - "Lenin, lenintsy, leninizm i razvitie sovetskoi nauki,", 1968 November 1 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Podkonvoinyi mir, 1971
      - Advertisements, 1972-1973 (Folder 5: 9)
      - Printed copies (Folder 5: 10)
      - Radio broadcast transcripts (Box 6)
        - General (Folder 6: 1)
        - Radio Liberty, 1972
          - January 5 (Folder 6: 2)
          - September (Folder 6: 3)
      - Reviews (Folder 6: 4)
    - "K konchine academika T. Lysenko,"., 1976 (Folder 6: 5)
      See also RADIO LIBERTY BROADCAST TRANSCRIPTS/Biology/ Lysenko, Trofim
    - "Ob ofitsioznoi antiizrail'skoi i antisemitskoi propagande v FRG v 1981 i ran'she," open letter (Folder 6: 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 6: 7)
  - About Germans, 1969-1983
    - General, n.d. (Folder 6: 8)
    - "Nemetskie emigranty iz gitlerovskoi Germanii,", n.d. (Folder 6: 9)
    - "Nemtsy,", n.d. (Folder 6: 10)
    - "Nemtsy: Pervootkryvateli,", n.d. (Folder 6: 11)
    - "Protiv natsistskikh ogul'nykh otsenok,", n.d. (Folder 6: 12)
    - "Adolf Gitler: Portret,", 1969 July 14 (Folder 6: 13)
    - "Gitler: Programma,", 1979 August 28 (Folder 6: 14)
    - "Beseda za kruglym stolom,", 1979 September 17 (Folder 6: 15)
    - "Natsistskaia lozh' v nemetskom TV,", 1981 September 25 (Folder 6: 16)
    - "Prava cheloveka po-nemetski,", 1981 December 16 (Folder 6: 17)
    - "O brakakh v nachale veka i o brakakh seichas v Germanii,", 1981 December 20 (Folder 6: 18)
    - "Snizhenie urovnia srednego obrazovaniia v FRG,", 1982 January 15 (Folder 6: 19)
    - "Diskussiia,", 1982 March 9 (Folder 6: 20)
    - "Programma v nemetskom FRG TV k 50-letiiu nachala szhiganiia gitlerovtsami knig,", 1983 May 8 (Folder 6: 21)
    - "K 50-letiiu sozzheniia knig: Vospominaniia o bavarskom poete Oskar Mariia Graf,", 1983 May 10 (Folder 6: 22)
    - "O sostoianii umov v FRG,", 1983 August 25 (Folder 6: 23)
    - "Beseda domokhoziaek o polozhenii domokhoziaek v sem'ie i obshchestve,", 1983 August 30 (Folder 6: 24)
    - "Otto Gan otkryvshii rasshcheplenie atoma,", 1983 September 29 (Folder 6: 25)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 6: 26)
  - About Jews
    - "Antisemitizm,", n.d. (Folder 6: 27)
    - "Chto menia bol'she vsego radovalo vo vsei zhizni,", n.d. (Folder 6: 28)
    - "Ded Lenina-evrei,", n.d. (Folder 6: 29)
    - "Dukh cherni,", n.d. (Folder 6: 30)
    - "Evrei,", n.d. (Folder 6: 31)
    - "Evrei i nemtsy,", n.d. (Folder 6: 32)
    - "Evrei iz Anglii-v lageria Kanady,", n.d. (Folder 6: 33)
    - "Evreiskii dukh,", n.d. (Folder 6: 34)
    - "Kak i pochemu razvilsia antisemitizm?", n.d. (Folder 6: 35)
    - "Kak nachalsia krizis 1929-1933 godov?", n.d. (Folder 6: 36)
    - "K reabilitatsii Trotskoko,", n.d. (Folder 6: 37)
    - "Likvidirovannye respubliki,", n.d. (Folder 6: 38)
    - "Mif o evreiskoi mirovoi vlasti,", n.d. (Folder 6: 39)
    - "Mysli o evreiakh i antisemitakh,", n.d. (Folder 6: 40)
    - "Mysli o evreiakh i antisemitizme,", n.d. (Folder 6: 41)
    - "Mysli ob antisemitizme i ego nositeliakh,", n.d. (Folder 6: 42)
    - "Natsional'naia nenavist,", n.d. (Folder 6: 43)
    - "Nemtsy i araby,", n.d. (Folder 6: 44)
    - "Nemtsy i evrei,", n.d. (Folder 6: 45)
    - "Neprichesannye mysli,", n.d. (Folder 6: 46)
    - "O vine Moskvy i zapada za genotsid evreev,", n.d. (Folder 6: 47)
    - "O iudeo-khristianskom obshchestve,", n.d. (Folder 6: 48)
    - "O pop muzyke,", n.d. (Folder 6: 49)
    - "O Rudolfe Gesse,", n.d. (Folder 6: 50)
    - "O Trotskom,", n.d. (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - "Ob ofitsioznoi antiizrail'skoi i antisemitskoi propagande v FRG v 1981 g. i ran'she," (Folder 7: 2)
    - "Ogranizatsiia Osvobozhdeniia Palestiny,", n.d. (Folder 7: 3)
    - "Otvety na navety,", n.d. (Folder 7: 4)
    - "Pochemu evrei izbegaiut rabotat' v shakhtakh, u domen ili martenov,", n.d. (Folder 7: 5)
    - "Pochemu evrei ne mstiat, ne mstitel'ny?", n.d. (Folder 7: 6)
    - "Pochemu russkie shovinisty spikhivaiut evreev v shakhty i na okrainy,", n.d. (Folder 7: 7)
    - "Prichiny antisemitizma: Opasnosti demokratii,", n.d. (Folder 7: 8)
    - "Prichiny sovremennogo sovetskogo antievreiskogo shovinizma,", n.d. (Folder 7: 9)
    - "Primechaniia k fil'mu Kholokost,", n.d. (Folder 7: 10)
    - "Primechaniia k statie Dana Il'ina,", n.d. (Folder 7: 11)
    - "Response to Slander," (Folder 7: 12)
    - "Svideteli rasskazali,", n.d. (Folder 7: 13)
    - "Trotskii: Fragmenty politicheskoi kharakteristiki,", n.d. (Folder 7: 14)
    - "V narode o evreiakh,", n.d. (Folder 7: 15)
    - "Velikie evrei,", n.d. (Folder 7: 16)
    - "Vostochnaia Prussiia,", n.d. (Folder 7: 17)
    - "Vtoraia ezhovshchina,", n.d. (Folder 7: 18)
    - "Zakat Evropy,", n.d. (Folder 7: 19)
    - "Televizionnaia seriia: Krakh nauki v Germanii- Gitlerovskii razgrom osnovy germanskogo nauchnogo dukha,", 1967 April 30 (Folder 7: 20)
    - "Kommunisty i sionizm,", 1967 December (Folder 7: 21)
    - "Nobelevskie premii,", 1970 (Folder 7: 22)
    - "Kak nemetskie media podderzhivaiut mif o natsii gospod,", 1983 March 10 (Folder 7: 23)
    - "Ob antisemitskikh dvizheniiakh v sovremennom mire," talk, Palo Alto, California, 1985 July 11 (Folder 7: 24)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 7: 25)
- RADIO LIBERTY GENERAL FILE, 1958-1982
  See also INCREMENTAL MATERIALS/Radio Liberty general file
  - Announcements (Folder 7: 26-27)
  - Appeals
    - General (Folder 7: 28)
    - Bukovskaia, Nina, "Obrashchenie v Komitet Prav Cheloveka FRG, k gospodinu George Meany, k pravitel'stvu i narodu Soedinennykh Shtatov Ameriki," (request to rescue her son Vladimir in Moscow), 1974
    - Gamsakhurdiia, Zviad, "Ob ispol'zovanii toksicheskogo oruzhiia organami KGB protiv Tbilisi,", 1975 (Folder 7: 29)
    - Orlov, IUrii, Valentin Turchin and Tatiana Khodorovitch, "Obrashchenie k obshchestvennosti zapadnykh stran,", 1975 (Folder 7: 30)
  - Articles and clippings (Folder 7: 31)
  - Articles and clippings (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Bulletin, 1966 (Folder 8: 2)
  - Clippings (Folder 8: 3-7)
  - Clippings (Box 9-13)
  - Correspondence (Box-folder 14: 1)
  - Flyers (Folder 14: 2)
  - Information bulletin, 1964-1973 (Folder 14: 3)
  - Internal documents (Folder 14: 4)
  - Lists
    - Faculty of the Institute on Study of the USSR (Folder 14: 5)
    - Russian Service staff (Folder 14: 6)
    - Soviet international organizations, 1971 (Folder 14: 7)
    - Soviet literary 'criminals,', 1968 (Folder 14: 8)
  - Memoranda
    - General. (Folder 14: 9-10)
      Includes memoranda by Edward Van Der Rhoer, 1970
    - General. (Box-folder 15: 1-2)
    - Research Department. (Folder 15: 3-6)
      Includes other material
    - Research Department. (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - Minutes of meetings (Folder 16: 2)
  - News clips, 1963-1982 (Folder 16: 3-4)
  - Newsletter (Folder 16: 5)
  - Notes (Folder 16: 6-7)
  - Notes (Box-folder 17: 1)
  - Open letters (Folder 17: 2)
  - Organizational chart (Folder 17: 3)
  - Outline of Radio Liberty's main problems and possible remedies, 1982 (Folder 17: 4)
  - Policy manual, 1958-1974 (Folder 17: 5-6)
  - Printed matter (Folder 17: 7)
  - Publications
    - Program Policy Guidelines, (in English and Russian), 1976 (Folder 17: 8)
    - Soviet Area Audience and Opinion Research, 1982 (Folder 17: 9)
  - Report (anonymous), 1975 (Folder 17: 10)
  - Summaries of Radio Liberty's Russian broadcasts, 1961-1981 (Box-folder 18: 1-3)
  - Surveys
    - General (Folder 18: 4-5)
    - Russian Service broadcasts (Folder 18: 4)
    - Russian Service broadcasts (Folder 19: 1-3)
  - Telephone directories. (Folder 19: 4-5)
    Includes addresses of personnel and schedules
- RADIO LIBERTY BROADCAST TRANSCRIPTS, 1963-1989
  - About
    - General (Box 20-25)
    - General (Box-folder 26: 1-3)
    - Agurskii, Mikhail
      - "Kul'tura, sobytiia, liudi,", 1975 (Folder 26: 4)
      - "Ideologicheskoe sostoianie sovetskogo obshchestva," #1-21, 1975-1976 (Folder 26: 5)
      - "Sostoianie obshchestva v totalitarnykh stranakh," #1-65, 1976 June 6 - 1977 (Folder 26: 6-7)
      - "Sostoianie obshchestva v totalitarnykh stranakh," #1-65, 1976 June 6 - 1977 (Box-folder 27: 1)
      - "Optimisticheskaia antiutopiia,", 1977 (Folder 27: 2)
    - Aldan-Semenov, Andrei, 1964
      Includes handwritten verses
      - "Eshche odna povest' o kontslageriakh" (Folder 27: 3)
      - "Sobytiia na fronte literatury i iskusstva v SSSR" (Folder 27: 4)
    - Atomic bomb. (Folder 27: 5-9)
      Includes broadcasts about Niels Bor, Max Born, Lev Landau, Robert Oppenheimer, Edward Teller
    - Babel, Isaak, "Vy pomnite?", 1978 (Box-folder 28: 1)
    - Berdiaev, Nikolai, 1966-1982 (Folder 28: 2)
      Includes his manuscript "Dukhi russkoi revoliutsii"
    - Biology
      - General
        - General (Folder 28: 3)
        - Vavilov, Nikolai (Folder 28: 4)
        - Lysenko, Trofim (Folder 28: 5-6)
      - Sociobiology (Folder 28: 7)
    - Bloch, Ernst, 1967-1977 (Folder 28: 8)
      Includes clippings
    - Bukharin, Nikolai, 1965-1988 (Folder 28: 9-10)
    - Bukovskii, Vladimir, "Korrespondentsiia iz Parizha," interview for Le Monde, 1977 (Folder 28: 11)
    - Demography - Soviet Union (Box 29)
      - General (Folder 29: 1-2)
      - Broadcast transcripts (Folder 29: 3)
    - Dialectical materialism
      - General (Folder 29: 4-5)
      - General (Box-folder 30: 1-5)
      - Broadcast transcripts (Box-folder 31: 1-4)
      - Broadcast transcripts (Box-folder 32: 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 32: 2-3)
    - Dictators (Folder 32: 4-6)
    - Dictators (Folder 33: 1)
    - Dissidents, 1980-1983 (Folder 33: 2)
    - Economics, 1970-1975 (Folder 33: 3)
    - Efremov, Ivan, 1969-1989 (Folder 33: 4)
    - Einstein, Albert, "The World as I See It,", 1964 (Folder 33: 5)
    - Forecasting
      - General, 1970-1977 (Folder 33: 6-7)
      - "Ot romana do nauki," #1-3, 1970 (Folder 33: 8)
      - "Puti v budushchee," #1-27, 1971 (Folder 33: 9)
      - "Puti v budushchee," #1-27, 1971 (Box-folder 34: 1)
    - Freedom of speech, "O svobode i nesvobode slova," #1-44, 1973-1975 (Folder 34: 2-5)
    - Galich, Aleksandr (Box-folder 35: 1-3)
      - "Pamiati Aleksandra Galicha," #1-10, 1982
      - Poetry (Folder 35: 4-6)
    - Genetics
      - General (Folder 35: 4-6)